<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop">
  <id>cataclysm-dda</id>
  <metadata_license>CC-BY-SA-3.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>CC-BY-SA-3.0</project_license>
  <name>Cataclysm: Dark Days Ahead</name>
  <summary>
    A turn-based survival game set in a post-apocalyptic world
  </summary>
  <description>
    <p>
      Struggle to survive in a harsh, persistent, procedurally
      generated world. Scavenge the remnants of a dead civilization
      for food, equipment, or, if you are lucky, a vehicle with a full
      tank of gas to get you the hell out of Dodge. Fight to defeat or
      escape from a wide variety of powerful monstrosities, from
      zombies to giant insects to killer robots and things far
      stranger and deadlier, and against the others like yourself,
      that want what you have...
    </p>
    <p>
      As your game begins, you awaken with hazy memories of violence
      and terror from when the world suddenly unravelled around
      you. Now you need to explore your surroundings, and secure food,
      water and safety. After that, who knows? Long term survival will
      mean tapping abilities you haven’t used before, learning to
      survive in this new environment and developing new skills.
    </p>
  </description>
  <content_rating type="oars-1.1">
    <content_attribute id="violence-fantasy">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="violence-bloodshed">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="violence-sexual">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="violence-desecration">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="violence-slavery">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="violence-worship">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="drugs-alcohol">moderate</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="drugs-narcotics">moderate</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="drugs-tobacco">moderate</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="sex-nudity">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="sex-themes">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="sex-homosexuality">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="sex-prostitution">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="sex-adultery">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="sex-appearance">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="language-profanity">moderate</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="language-humor">mild</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="language-discrimination">intense</content_attribute>
  </content_rating>
  <url type="homepage">
    https://www.cataclysmdda.org
  </url>
  <url type="bugtracker">
    https://github.com/CleverRaven/Cataclysm-DDA/issues
  </url>
  <url type="translate">
    https://www.transifex.com/cataclysm-dda-translators/cataclysm-dda/
  </url>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">cataclysm-dda.desktop</launchable>
  <provides>
    <binary>cataclysm-tiles</binary>
  </provides>
  <releases>
    <release version="0.D Danny" date="2019-03-08">
      <description>
        <p>
          The Danny release is characterized by MORE. More UI polish,
          more features, more content, more long-asked-for
          changes. It’s the longest-lived and largest in every way
          release we’ve ever done, and we hope to never do it
          again. Future releases are planned for roughly 6-month
          intervals. This release is made up of 37,604 commits
          authored by over 700 contributors, and it roughly doubled
          the number of everything in the game, items, monsters, map
          buildings, you name it, we doubled it.
        </p>
        <p>
          It’s honestly way too huge to summarize in any meaningful
          way, but here are the absolute biggest changes, and you’ll
          just have to dig into the changelog or the game itself for
          more detail.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            Many quality of life enhancements such as auto-pulp,
            autopickup, batch actions, interacting with adjacent items
            and improved long-action handling.
          </li>
          <li>
            Pixel minimap for tiles mode.
          </li>
          <li>
            Guns accept magazines when appropriate.
          </li>
          <li>
            Player stamina stat that is burned by running and other
            physical exertion.
          </li>
          <li>
            Player faction base that allows incremental growth and
            autonomous work by NPCs.
          </li>
          <li>
            The player remembers terrain and furniture they have seen.
          </li>
          <li>
            Carrying racks for small vehicles.
          </li>
          <li>
            Vehicle system (speed, fuel consumption, terrain effects)
            overhaul.
          </li>
          <li>
            Overhauled nutrition, food spoilage and food state changes
            (freezing).
          </li>
          <li>
            Overhauled bomb fragment handling.
          </li>
          <li>
            NPC dialogue support, group commands, tactical
            instructions and backstories.
          </li>
          <li>
            Dynamic Lighting.
          </li>
          <li>
            Roughly DOUBLED the amount of in-game content.
          </li>
          <li>
            Unheard-of levels of bugfixing.
          </li>
          <li>
            Full translations for Chinese, German, Japanese, Polish
            and Russian.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.C Cooper" date="2015-03-09">
      <p>
        The Cooper release is named in honor of the new monster
        infighting system. Now you can sit back and watch as your
        enemies tear each other to pieces! Don’t get too close though,
        they’re still out for your blood.
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          This release also brings the long-requested DeathCam system,
          which lets you see the aftermath of the glorious fireball or
          atrocious train wreck that was your demise.
        </li>
        <li>
          Gun users will notice a new aiming menu: you can now spend
          time to steady your aim. Do you take the shot now, or wait
          until the zombie gets a little closer?
        </li>
        <li>
          Tailoring-oriented survivors (and who isn’t?) will note the
          new tailor’s kit item, which lets you add insulation or
          protective patches to your clothes.
        </li>
        <li>
          Survivors with gigantic death-mobiles may appreciate the new
          turret options, including being able to enable/disable
          individual turrets, and being able to fire some turrets
          manually.
        </li>
        <li>
          Finally, for survivors with, shall we say, “well-stocked”
          bases, there are massive improvements to performance when
          there are many thousands of items nearby.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </release>
    <release version="0.B Brin" date="2014-11-17">
      <p>
        The Brin release is named in honor of significant improvements
        to PC/NPC relations.
      </p>
      <p>
        This release, containing over 9,000 commits (@kevingranade
        counted) brings an unheard-of amount of new features and
        content, most of which wants you dead.
      </p>
      <p>
        Start your adventure in a wide variety of different locations,
        with a selection of different starting scenarios, now with
        unique character traits. Explore new locations, some of which
        are ridiculously big (did somebody say ‘mall’?), and some of
        which have inhabitants that don’t want to eat you for a
        change. Vehicles have gotten some love, and now form a basis
        for an electrical network should you desire to build one. If
        you’ve ever wanted to strap a C4 pack onto an RC car and drive
        it under a Zombie Hulk, you got your chance.
      </p>
    </release>
    <release version="0.A Kaufman" date="2014-03-22">
      <p>
        The Kaufman is named in honor of a huge expansion to
        Cataclysm’s mutation system.  The release, our largest yet
        also brings innumerable bugfixes, performance enhancements,
        new items, a long-awaited module manager, new monsters,
        fullscreen mode, better mouse support, new map tiles and an
        unheard-of level of stability.
      </p>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
