<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop">
  <id>org.cataclysmdda.CataclysmDDA</id>
  <metadata_license>CC-BY-SA-3.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>CC-BY-SA-3.0</project_license>
  <name>Cataclysm: Dark Days Ahead</name>
  <summary>
    A turn-based survival game set in a post-apocalyptic world
  </summary>
  <description>
    <p>
      Struggle to survive in a harsh, persistent, procedurally
      generated world. Scavenge the remnants of a dead civilization
      for food, equipment, or, if you are lucky, a vehicle with a full
      tank of gas to get you the hell out of Dodge. Fight to defeat or
      escape from a wide variety of powerful monstrosities, from
      zombies to giant insects to killer robots and things far
      stranger and deadlier, and against the others like yourself,
      that want what you have...
    </p>
    <p>
      As your game begins, you awaken with hazy memories of violence
      and terror from when the world suddenly unraveled around
      you. Now you need to explore your surroundings, and secure food,
      water and safety. After that, who knows? Long term survival will
      mean tapping abilities you haven’t used before, learning to
      survive in this new environment and developing new skills.
    </p>
  </description>
  <categories>
    <category>Game</category>
    <category>RolePlaying</category>
  </categories>
  <content_rating type="oars-1.1">
    <content_attribute id="violence-fantasy">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="violence-bloodshed">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="violence-sexual">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="violence-desecration">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="violence-slavery">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="violence-worship">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="drugs-alcohol">moderate</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="drugs-narcotics">moderate</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="drugs-tobacco">moderate</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="sex-nudity">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="sex-themes">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="sex-homosexuality">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="sex-prostitution">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="sex-adultery">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="sex-appearance">intense</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="language-profanity">moderate</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="language-humor">mild</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="language-discrimination">intense</content_attribute>
  </content_rating>
  <url type="homepage">
    https://www.cataclysmdda.org
  </url>
  <url type="bugtracker">
    https://github.com/CleverRaven/Cataclysm-DDA/issues
  </url>
  <url type="translate">
    https://www.transifex.com/cataclysm-dda-translators/cataclysm-dda/
  </url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">
    https://github.com/CleverRaven/Cataclysm-DDA/
  </url>
  <url type="contribute">
    https://cataclysmdda.org/contributions/
  </url>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">org.cataclysmdda.CataclysmDDA.desktop</launchable>
  <provides>
    <binary>cataclysm-tiles</binary>
  </provides>

  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CleverRaven/Cataclysm-DDA/c0eed669da247c8e9be9a5176aaf3cbd922e48a7/data/screenshots/menu.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CleverRaven/Cataclysm-DDA/c0eed669da247c8e9be9a5176aaf3cbd922e48a7/data/screenshots/game.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CleverRaven/Cataclysm-DDA/c0eed669da247c8e9be9a5176aaf3cbd922e48a7/data/screenshots/credits.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>

  <developer id="org.cataclysmdda">
    <name>Kevin Granade and Contributors</name>
  </developer>
  <releases>
    <release version="0.H" date="2024-07-22">
      <description>
        <p>
          I'm proud to announce that the Cataclysm: Dark Days Ahead 0.H "Herbert" release is here!
          With an 11 month Gestation (before forking) and a 10 month delivery (after forking),
          we once again utterly failed to limit the scope of work with a release, the 0.H
          development process has been the longest in many releases, packing in thousands of new
          pieces of content, massive performance improvements, and IMO more polish than we've ever
          seen in a DDA release. A huge group of about 450 people contributed to this release,
          about 200 for the first time this release. All together we changed about 12 million
          lines of code and data across about 5,500 files, adding about 5,000 game entities in the
          core game and another 5,000 in mods. This time around we handled the release process
          differently, following a more traditional process where we called 0.H "feature complete"
          all the way back in January of 2024 and moved it to a dedicated fork for bugfixing.
          Since then we've created new infrastructure to manage the stabilization process,
          fixed many many bugs, and backported a limited number of key features from the
          experimental branch. Whether this new approach really hits its stride is yet to be seen,
          but I'm hopeful next cycle can be shorter now that the infrastructure is in place.
        </p>
        <p>
          Feature wise, we've seen the addition of biomes, where traveling East now leads to larger
          cities to a point, then the lands ends in an ocean. Travelling West leads to sparser human
          settlements and more wilderness. Portal storms now spawn and move around on the map, you
          can either hunker down or move to avoid them (or chase them if you're so inclined), and an
          unprecedented amount of new and interesting content has been added to their chaotic mix.
          After years of hard work, 3D vision has improved greatly, bugs are few and far between,
          and thanks to this feature we can see a lot more interactivity between Z levels. It still
          defaults off, but you don't need to be afraid of it. Our accidental bespoke scripting
          framework, the EOC system, has been greatly expanded and many, many features have been
          overhauled to take advantage of it. This allows an enormous flexibility of events in both
          mainline and mods without ever touching a compiler. Multiple new boss-tier encounters have
          been added for late game challenge, though I don't want to spoil them here. Now you will
          know why you fear the night. The number of proficiencies has increased greatly for this
          version, roughly doubling the number of proficiencies you can learn, with unique effects.
          We've seen an expansion of the proficiency framework in some of the directions desired
          initially, allowing proficiencies to confer more than just crafting bonuses. Practice
          actions have also filled out, providing a smooth path for skill gain instead of grinding
          crafting or other activities. This version should see an end to repeatedly crafting and
          uncrafting a simple object to grind skills, allowing you to streamline the process to
          represent your character studying and practicing, spending character time but not so much
          player time. You'll also notice other savings in player time, we've found a number of
          places to speed up key code and drastically reduce waiting times, making for a much more
          responsive experience.
        </p>
	<p>
          Try it out. It's the best DDA yet.
	</p>
      </description>
      <url type="details">
        https://github.com/CleverRaven/Cataclysm-DDA/tree/0.H-branch/data/changelog.txt</url>
    </release>
    <release version="0.G Gaiman" date="2023-03-01">
      <description>
        <p>
          We are proud to announce that 0.G “Gaiman” stable release has arrived! Two years have
          passed since the release of the stable version 0.F “Frank”, two years of unprecedented
          turmoil in the real world that delayed our planned release of the next stable. These two
          years have seen many IRL job changes among the dev team, new contributors to CleverRaven,
          and a couple of babies joining members' families. The 0.G release is more than double the
          size of the 0.F release, a distinction that we keep trying and failing to avoid. Even more
          than previous stable versions, this release features a massive range of bugfixes, code and
          content additions, and new features. 10,293 new game entities were added, 11,643,312 lines
          of source code were inserted, and 5,022,361 lines were deleted. This included several new
          language translations, multiple new tilesets; including some isometric tileset demos, and
          multiple new mods in addition to base game content and features.
        </p>
        <p>
          This cycle was started, tilting at our perennial windmill of a six to nine month release
          cycle. Shortly thereafter, Covid locked down the world but not contributions to DDA! There
          are many incredible changes that have entered the game and several ancient issues that
          have been closed. The skill system has been greatly expanded with many new proficiencies
          and many new ways to learn them, as well as the groundwork for practice-based skill
          improvement, including a skill rust system that doesn't suck because it caps effective
          skill loss and regenerates faster than regular skill gain. Appliance based stationary
          power grids now exist. Turning vehicles now present complete walls that block out
          monsters, fields and more from crossing from the outside to the inside of the vehicle. Map
          memory is now unlimited, so you will no longer forget places you haven't been to recently.
          Cardio has finally been modeled so that your endurance will increase if you spend your
          days running and working hard or exercising. Perspiration is now modeled, your character
          running around the middle of summer in full plate mail won't immediately overheat. Now
          your character will perspire and thirst will increase until you are dehydrated at which
          point overheating will begin. Hydrate yourselves accordingly!
        </p>
        <p>
          In addition to the above issue/request resolving features above, there are a number of new
          features that haven't necessarily been on the roadmap for a long time but came to fruition
          during this experimental cycle. The amount of UI based contributions has gone through the
          roof this cycle and created tons of options around how your fully customizable sidebar
          looks, the color theme for your UI is also fully customizable with multiple shipped
          options, along with updates and improvements to action explanations, tutorials and the
          github process itself, which while not visible to people who only play the game makes a
          huge difference in the quality and amount of contributions added to Cataclysm: Dark Days
          Ahead. You can now passively purify water by boiling it by placing it in a fireproof
          container on a fire or near an extreme heat source. A new hobby tab in character creation
          allows you to choose traits and skills that go together that represent how you spent your
          time before the end of the world. Monster weak points now exist, allowing your strikes to
          critically hit. You can learn proficiencies that will increase your likelihood to
          critically hit these weak points by researching and dissecting monsters. Speaking of
          monsters, we've adjusted the aggression system so that some more intelligent monsters will
          recognize whether they were attacked by another monster or the player and will remain
          passive or gain hostility depending on who harmed them. A lone zombie will no longer turn
          a pack of wild dogs permanently hostile to you. Finally, Effect on Condition brings a
          scripting pseudo language to Cataclysm. Some of its key uses in 0.G have been the
          introduction of portal storms, NPC faction development over time, the ability to take over
          a follower after pc death, and random encounters in already explored maps.
        </p>
        <p>
          During this time modders have added a half dozen new in repo mods: Innawoods for the
          survival from scratch you crave, Backrooms which takes place in the neverending backrooms
          dimension, Massachusetts mod for people who desire geographic accuracy, Xedra Evolved a
          science fantasy mod with weird magic and vampirism, Tropicataclysm for your Cataclysm at a
          warmer latitude, and the Megafauna mod which targets an ancient epoch with creatures that
          outsize our modern equivalents, similar to Dinomod. In addition to this Magiclysm,
          Dinomod, and Aftershock have received dozens of new PRs each to a scale that would be
          equal to or larger than paid DLC for a AAA game.
        </p>
        <p>
          We, the DDA team, have had a great time creating new content and worlds to explore and we
          hope that you enjoy them and if a mood takes you, that you join us in creating more in the
          future.
        </p>
      </description>
      <url type="details">
        https://github.com/CleverRaven/Cataclysm-DDA/tree/0.G-branch/data/changelog.txt</url>
    </release>

    <release version="0.F Frank" date="2021-07-02">
      <description>
        <p>
          After a long and anticlimactic buildup, we are pleased to
          announce the release of stable version 0.F "Frank" of
          Cataclysm: Dark Days Ahead! Like our previous stable
          versions, this release features an expansive range of
          bugfixes, code and content additions, and new features.
          4,500 new game entities were added, 123,162 lines of source
          code were inserted, and 77,727 lines were deleted.
        </p>
        <p>
          The goal was to have a smaller and more manageable release
          this cycle, which was an utter failure, as it took well over
          a year and by several measures was even larger than the 0.E
          cycle.
        </p>
        <p>
          We'd overall characterize 0.F as a release with a lot of
          content and polish. Compared to 0.E, you may find it a
          little more difficult (the pendulum swings ever back and
          forth), but we think also more rewarding.
        </p>
        <p>
          The most obvious feature of 0.F is the addition of nested
          inventory, the ability to store items in containers and
          have them behave as you'd expect. This is probably the most
          long awaited and highly requested feature of the past five
          years of development.
        </p>
        <p>
          Besides pockets, 0.F features the addition of achievements
          for fun and bragging rights, a proficiency system to
          represent more refined skill knowledge, blood loss mechanics
          for you and your enemies, weariness that builds as you push
          yourself to your limits, vehicles that can drive up and down
          z-levels (and bridges that are above rivers, enabling more
          navigable rivers, as a result), and a vast host of new
          content from new monsters and evolutions to new quests and items.
        </p>
        <p>
          On the mod side, Magiclysm, Aftershock, and Dinomod have all
          grown expansively, including new artifact and enchantment
          systems that have impacted content in the main game.
          And much more, too much to list here.
        </p>
        <p>
          Players coming from the last stable will notice a switch
          towards encouraging looting over crafting, especially in
          the early game, and will have to be cautious about
          overextending themselves in the beginning of their survival
          effort. As usual, you'll want to avoid getting into combat
          with multiple zombies in an open area. However, you can also
          have 'grab bags' of useful gear and tools, allowing you to
          toss your loot sack to the floor to engage in an
          unencumbered melee battle with zombies!
        </p>
        <p>
          All in all, as usual, we're deeply excited about this new
          version, and look forward to continuing to make your
          survival difficult in the months to come.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Nested Containers rationalize inventory management and enable dropping and retrieving go-bags during fights.</li>
          <li>Achievements track your deeds and misdeeds across games.</li>
          <li>Proficiencies better represent deeper knowledge required for various endeavors, mostly crafting.</li>
          <li>Bleeding added to both the player and monsters as the first step toward a more comprehensive wound and wound treatment system.</li>
          <li>Weariness tracking added to represent longer-term physical exhaustion.</li>
          <li>Elevated bridges over navigable rivers added, allowing better navigability while using boats.</li>
          <li>Large-scale audit of weapon and armor values for better representativeness and consistency.</li>
          <li>Improved armor handling by separating ballistic damage into its own damage type.</li>
          <li>Pervasive performance enhancements throughout the game.</li>
          <li>Tileset vehicle support for more cohesive vehicle rendering.</li>
          <li>Aftershock changes direction to a total conversion mod with a new far-future setting on a frozen world.</li>
          <li>Dinomod added 238 dinosaurs, pterosaurs, mosasaurs, and dino-related NPCs with missions and dino locations.</li>
          <li>Added many dino features, including zombie, fungal, evolved, bionic, baby, and mutant dino variants.</li>
          <li>Dinomod added many dino interactions, including farming, riding, butchering, cooking, and special attacks.</li>
          <li>Magiclysm added a huge content update including many new traits called Attunements that switch up gameplay at the endgame.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
      <url type="details">https://github.com/CleverRaven/Cataclysm-DDA/blob/0.F/data/changelog.txt</url>
    </release>
    <release version="0.E Ellison" date="2020-04-01">
      <description>
        <p>
          The Ellison release adds a huge number of features and content
          that make the world feel more alive. From being able to climb
          onto building rooftops or hide behind cars, to building a camp
          for your followers in the wilderness, to exploring the new
          river and lake systems on a boat or raft, everything is more
          immersive and consistent. Also more STUFF. I didn’t think we
          would ever double the number of game entities with a release
          again, but we did.
        </p>
        <p>
          We aimed at a 6 month release cycle, and ended up spending 9
          months adding features at a breakneck pace and 3 months
          putting the brakes on and stabilizing. I can’t honestly say
          that’s a huge disappointment, though toward the end the rest
          of the development team was really chomping at the bit to get
          back to feature work, so we’ll need to continue to adjust.
        </p>
        <p>
          We built a huge amount of infrastructure for having the game
          check its own consistency, which has and is going to continue
          to contribute to the amazing pace of feature and content
          additions we are experiencing. The development team is also
          larger and at the same time more cohesive than it has ever
          been before.
        </p>
        <p>
          Explore all the new features with the attached release
          archives. Speaking of exploring, the list of available
          tilesets has shuffled a bit, so this is a great time to find
          your new favorite.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Long distance automove feature for walking, driving and boating.</li>
          <li>Extensive bugfixes to inter-level interactivity, on by default.</li>
          <li>Riding animals and animal-pulled vehicles.</li>
          <li>More flexible Basecamp construction options.</li>
          <li>Default starting date changed to mid-spring for better survivability.</li>
          <li>Time advancement is rationalized, a turn is now one second.</li>
          <li>Extensive river and lake systems, and boat support for navigating them.</li>
          <li>Expanded NPC usefulness and interactivity.</li>
          <li>Massive increases in location variety and consistency, especially rooftops.</li>
          <li>Expansion of mi-go faction with new enemies and locations.</li>
          <li>Batteries now store charge instead of being pseudo-items.</li>
          <li>Overhaul and rebalance of martial arts.</li>
          <li>Zombie grabbing and biting more manageable and predictable.</li>
          <li>Overhauled stamina and damage recovery for grittier gameplay.</li>
          <li>Crouching movement mode allows hiding.</li>
          <li>Magiclysm and Aftershock mods have first class support within the game.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
      <url type="details">https://github.com/CleverRaven/Cataclysm-DDA/blob/0.E/data/changelog.txt</url>
    </release>
    <release version="0.D Danny" date="2019-03-08">
      <description>
        <p>
          The Danny release is characterized by MORE. More UI polish,
          more features, more content, more long-asked-for
          changes. It’s the longest-lived and largest in every way
          release we’ve ever done, and we hope to never do it
          again. Future releases are planned for roughly 6-month
          intervals. This release is made up of 37,604 commits
          authored by over 700 contributors, and it roughly doubled
          the number of everything in the game, items, monsters, map
          buildings, you name it, we doubled it.
        </p>
        <p>
          It’s honestly way too huge to summarize in any meaningful
          way, but here are the absolute biggest changes, and you’ll
          just have to dig into the changelog or the game itself for
          more detail.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            Many quality of life enhancements such as auto-pulp,
            autopickup, batch actions, interacting with adjacent items
            and improved long-action handling.
          </li>
          <li>
            Pixel minimap for tiles mode.
          </li>
          <li>
            Guns accept magazines when appropriate.
          </li>
          <li>
            Player stamina stat that is burned by running and other
            physical exertion.
          </li>
          <li>
            Player faction base that allows incremental growth and
            autonomous work by NPCs.
          </li>
          <li>
            The player remembers terrain and furniture they have seen.
          </li>
          <li>
            Carrying racks for small vehicles.
          </li>
          <li>
            Vehicle system (speed, fuel consumption, terrain effects)
            overhaul.
          </li>
          <li>
            Overhauled nutrition, food spoilage and food state changes
            (freezing).
          </li>
          <li>
            Overhauled bomb fragment handling.
          </li>
          <li>
            NPC dialogue support, group commands, tactical
            instructions and backstories.
          </li>
          <li>
            Dynamic Lighting.
          </li>
          <li>
            Roughly DOUBLED the amount of in-game content.
          </li>
          <li>
            Unheard-of levels of bugfixing.
          </li>
          <li>
            Full translations for Chinese, German, Japanese, Polish
            and Russian.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.C Cooper" date="2015-03-09">
      <description>
        <p>
          The Cooper release is named in honor of the new monster
          infighting system. Now you can sit back and watch as your
          enemies tear each other to pieces! Don’t get too close though,
          they’re still out for your blood.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            This release also brings the long-requested DeathCam system,
            which lets you see the aftermath of the glorious fireball or
            atrocious train wreck that was your demise.
          </li>
          <li>
            Gun users will notice a new aiming menu: you can now spend
            time to steady your aim. Do you take the shot now, or wait
            until the zombie gets a little closer?
          </li>
          <li>
            Tailoring-oriented survivors (and who isn’t?) will note the
            new tailor’s kit item, which lets you add insulation or
            protective patches to your clothes.
          </li>
          <li>
            Survivors with gigantic death-mobiles may appreciate the new
            turret options, including being able to enable/disable
            individual turrets, and being able to fire some turrets
            manually.
          </li>
          <li>
            Finally, for survivors with, shall we say, “well-stocked”
            bases, there are massive improvements to performance when
            there are many thousands of items nearby.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.B Brin" date="2014-11-17">
      <description>
        <p>
          The Brin release is named in honor of significant improvements
          to PC/NPC relations.
        </p>
        <p>
          This release, containing over 9,000 commits (@kevingranade
          counted) brings an unheard-of amount of new features and
          content, most of which wants you dead.
        </p>
        <p>
          Start your adventure in a wide variety of different locations,
          with a selection of different starting scenarios, now with
          unique character traits. Explore new locations, some of which
          are ridiculously big (did somebody say ‘mall’?), and some of
          which have inhabitants that don’t want to eat you for a
          change. Vehicles have gotten some love, and now form a basis
          for an electrical network should you desire to build one. If
          you’ve ever wanted to strap a C4 pack onto an RC car and drive
          it under a Zombie Hulk, you got your chance.
        </p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.A Kaufman" date="2014-03-22">
      <description>
        <p>
          The Kaufman is named in honor of a huge expansion to
          Cataclysm’s mutation system.  The release, our largest yet
          also brings innumerable bugfixes, performance enhancements,
          new items, a long-awaited module manager, new monsters,
          fullscreen mode, better mouse support, new map tiles and an
          unheard-of level of stability.
        </p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
